Register of the Dušan T. Simovic writings
Hoover Institution Archives
Dušan T. Simovic writings
1941-1962
92076
Simovic, Dušan T., 1882-1962
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Consists of correspondence, speeches, a memoir and a diary documenting Simović's military career, Serbian military operations during World War I, political conditions in Yugoslavia prior to World War II, the Yugoslav coup d'état of 27 March 1941, and the government-in-exile in London during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1992.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
28 October 1882 Born in Kragujevac, Serbia
1900 Graduated, Belgrade Military Academy, Yugoslavia
1912-1913 Served in the Balkan wars; promoted to the rank of General Staff Major
1914-1918 Served in World War I; promoted to the rank of Lieutenant Colonel
1918-1940 Delegate of the Serbian Government and the Supreme Command at the National Council of Slovenes, Croats, and Serbs in Zagreb in 1918; devoted his military career to the Air Force
1936-1940 Served as chief of the Air Force and commander-in-chief of the Royal Yugoslav Army
1938-1940 Served as Chief of the General Staff of the Yugoslav Royal Army; forced to resign in 1940 after advocating resistance in case of a German attack
25 March 1941 Tripartite Pact with the Germans signed by Dragiša Cvetković, Prime Minister of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia, in Vienna
27 March 1941 Led a military coup of Royal Yugoslav officers to overthrow the government of Dragiša Cvetković
1941-1942 Served as Prime Minister and Chief of the General Staff of the Yugoslav Army
13 April 1941 Held the last session of the Royal Yugoslav government in Nikšić, Montenegro
15 April 1941 Escorted King Petar II out of Yugoslavia to safety
April-June 1941 Served in the Yugoslav government-in-exile in Jerusalem and London
11 January 1942 Dismissed as Prime Minister of Yugoslavia over political disagreements within the exiled Yugoslav government
1943 Retired; joined the "People's Liberation Movement"
1945-1946 Returned to Belgrade; participated as a witness at the trial of Draža Mihailović
1962 Died in Belgrade
Scope and Content of Collection
Contains correspondence, speeches, a memoir, and a diary documenting Simović's military career, Serbian military operations during World War I, political conditions in Yugoslavia prior to World War II, the Yugoslav coup d'état of 27 March 1941, and the government-in-exile in London during World War II. The materials provide insight into the events surrounding the military coup and record Simović's thoughts as a leading military and public figure in Royal Yugoslavia, especially the war years Simović spent with the government-in-exile in London.
The Correspondence mainly includes exchanges with exiled Yugoslav government leaders regarding the wartime situation in Yugoslavia. Of particular interest are Simović's letters to King Petar II, expressing his position on dissension within the Yugoslav government-in-exile in London, and correspondence with Winston Churchill referring to the war in Yugoslavia and Simović's offer to serve in His Majesty's government as a retired Royal Yugoslav general.
Transcripts of Simović's Speeches, broadcast on London radio, express his position on the wartime situation in Yugoslavia, the exile community, and the Balkan region.
The Writings contain preliminary drafts and related material for an extensive memoir titled "Uspomene, Autobiografia," documenting Simović's military and political career, his role during the Balkan Wars, World War I, Yugoslavia in the inter-war years, and wartime in exile in London. The final draft of "Uspomene Autobiografija" was transcribed by Dragiša Ristić. Fragments of writings and notes contain Simović's reflections on events surrounding the Yugoslav Army surrender and the "Cairo Affair," as well as a pamphlet titled Dokument o Jugoslaviji (Document of Yugoslavia) published by Dragiša Cvetković.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
World War, 1914-1918--Serbia.; World War, 1939-1945--Yugoslavia.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; Yugoslavia--History--Axis occupation, 1941-1945.; Yugoslavia--Politics and government--1918-1945.; Yugoslavia--Foreign relations--1918-1945.; Statesmen--Yugoslavia.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, 1941-1956.
  Contains letters, telegrams, and enclosures, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Astor, Colonel, 1942 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Churchill, Winston S., 1942-1956 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Ćurčić, P. and Jovo Džanjevic, 1942 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Eden, Anthony, 1941 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Fotić, Konstantin, 1941-1942 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Jovanović, Slobodan, 1942 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Jurišić-Šturm, 1941 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Knežević, Živan L., 1942 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Krnjević, Juraj, 1945 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Petar II, King of Yugolsvia, 1941-1945 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Simović, Milioš, 1945 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Subašić, Ivan, 1945 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Šutej, J., 1942 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Trifunović, Miloš, 1943 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Tsouderos, Emmanouil, 1942 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Velebit, Velmir, 1945 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Živković, Petar, 1945 (Folder 1: 17)
  - General, 1942 (Folder 1: 18)
- Speeches, 1941-1944. (Box 1)
  Consists of transcripts of radio broadcasts and speeches, arranged in two groups
  - Radio broadcasts, London (Folder 1: 19)
    - September 1941. "O Novoj Evropi i o Novom Balkanu," talk to Serbs, Croats and Slovenes (Folder 1: 19)
    - 31 March 1943. "The Importance of the Events 31 March 1941" talk, The Royal Yugoslav Society, London (Folder 1: 19)
    - 19 February 1944 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Message to Yugoslav exiles in Brasilia, Brazil, 1943 (Folder 1: 20)
- Writings, 1941-1962. (Box 1)
  Includes preliminary and unfinished drafts of an autobiography, notes, newspaper clippings, arranged in three groups: memoir, diary, and fragments
  - "Uspomene, Autobiografija" memoir draft, undated (Box 1)
    - "Content and Preface for Autobiography" (Folder 1: 21)
    - "Early Life" (Folder 1: 22)
    - "The Balkan Wars" (Folder 1: 23)
    - "World War I" (Folder 1: 24)
    - "Formation of Yugoslavia, 1918-1937" (Folder 1: 25-27)
    - "Preparation for War, 1938-1940" (Folder 1: 28)
    - "Nedić, Prince Paul and close ties with Germany, 1940" (Folder 1: 29)
    - "German Invasion, April-June 1941" (Folder 1: 30)
    - "Exile in London, 1941-1944" (Folder 1: 31-37)
    - "End of War, Return to Yugoslavia, 1945-1948" (Folder 1: 38)
    - Final draft transcribed by Dragiša Ristić, 1950 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Diary, 1941-1944 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Fragments, 1941-1962 (Box 2)
    - Balkan Wars notes 1912-1913, 1962 (Folder 2: 3)
    - "Jugoslavia na Prekretnici,", 1939-1943 (Folder 2: 4)
    - World War I notes, undated (Folder 2: 5)
    - The coup, 27 March 1941 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Reconciliation and events surrounding the coup, 27 March 1941 (Folder 2: 7)
    - Dragutin Savić's testimony on the events on 27 March 1941 (Folder 2: 8)
    - "Last Negotiation with Axis,", circa 1941 (Folder 2: 9)
    - "Pitanje Kapitulacije Vojske,", circa 1942 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Dokument o Jugoslaviji (Document of Yugoslavia) brochure by Dragiša Cvetković with comments, 1957 (Folder 2: 11)
    - "Slom Stare Jugoslavije" by Ferdo Čulinović, 1958 (Folder 2: 12)
    - "Cairo Affair," an excerpt, circa 1941 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Notes, 1944-1945 (Folder 2: 14)